Finding Aid for the John Keith Benton Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John Keith Benton Papers
1940s-1950s
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0697
3.25 linear_feet
Biographical Sketch
John Keith Benton was born on May 24, 1896 in Banks, Alabama to Martha Frederick and Arthur Franklin Benton. Benton joined the Army in 1917 and served as a pilot in WWI. He graduated from Birmingham Southern College with a Bachelor of Arts degree and received a Bachelor of Arts in Divinity from Yale University. Upon leaving Yale he attended Edinburgh University where he received his PhD. Benton soon took the position as professor of philosophy and psychology at Drew University in New Jersey before moving to Vanderbilt University in 1939 to become dean of the School of Religion. Over the course of his career, Benton gave numerous sermons and addresses but also published several theological articles, many of which are preserved in his collection.
Benton is remembered as the presiding Dean when Vanderbilt’s Divinity School began to admit African American applicants in 1952; he is reported to have encouraged Chancellor Harvie Branscomb and other university officials to examine their University policy on race-based admissions.
Benton served as Dean of Vanderbilt’s Divinity School from 1939 to 1956. While Dean, Benton spearheaded the construction of a new home for Vanderbilt’s Divinity school. Benton died on August 21, 1956 before the building was completed, prompting the University to name the building Benton Chapel in honor of his service. Benton Chapel still serves as the primary multidenominational house of worship and center of the Divinity School on the university’s campus.
Scope and Content Note
The John Keith Benton Papers are composed of 3.25 linear feet of sermons, articles, research, correspondence and photographs from his career as a pastor and Vanderbilt Dean. The dates of the collection range from the 1940s to the mid-1950s. It is divided into five series.
Sermons—transcripts of sermons given by Benton
Research Notes—notes and research on potential sermons and other lectures by Benton
Programs—programs from Benton’s lectures and sermons as well as other church bulletins and programs
Writings—articles and addresses by Benton
Miscellaneous Documents—contains correspondence, drafts by others, as well as Benton’s Freedom Foundation Award and World War I pilot cap
Provenance Statement
The Benton Papers were donated by Ms. Lyn Lowrey Honig to Vanderbilt University Special Collections in 2008.
- Sermons
  - “What Can I Depend On?”, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “Canons of Sermon Criticism”, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - “Zedekiah—Ally Way to the Lord”, 1945/1947/1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Fodderwings”, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - “God’s Remembrance,” Program, Tennessee Annual Conference, Notes, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - “Thanksgiving”, 1949/1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - “Forest Fire”, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Heart Trouble”, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - “All or None,” Notes & Related Documents, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - “Integrity,” Personal Notes, Worship Program, West End Methodist Church, 1953/1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - “The Christian Answer”, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - “So Little Interest”, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - “Don’t Get In Your Own Way”, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - “Christianity and Social Reform”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - “Death Steals the Show,” Notes & Related Documents, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - “Freedom and Happiness”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - “God”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - “A House to Live In,” Personal Notes/Drafts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - “How Rapidly Should I Expect Evil to Overcome?” Note Cards, Sermon, Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - “Human Rights,” & Related Documents, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - “The Meaning to Youth & The terms of God, Christ, and Holy Spirit”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - “Sensitivity”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - “Students Coin Epigrams”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - “Toward A Christian Interpretation of Man”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - “What Difference Does Easter Make?”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - “Who is a Christian?”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - “Vital Christian Living”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Research Notes
  - 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - “Behold I Stand at the Door”, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “The Light of the World”, August 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - “Fellowship of His Suffering”, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - “Security”, January 14, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - “The Great Decision”, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “Of Good Report”, June 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - “Growing Up in the XU Faith”, October 12, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - “The Contributions of Judaism to Christianity”, February 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - “Can a Modern Man be Optimistic?”, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - “Life Everlasting”, April 16, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - “Notes on Christian Belief”, Fall 1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - “The Church as Prophet and Teacher”, Fall 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - “Centerpiece of Despair”, January 7, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - “Heroes/Knights of Greater Congressional”, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - “Disciples for Vital Christian Living”, August 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - “Faith”, August 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - “Sensitivity”, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sermon Notes & Ideas, 1940-1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Sermon Notes I, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sermon Notes II, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sermon Notes III, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Potential Sermon Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - “What is Your Name?”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - “Love” & “The Ties of Brotherhood”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - “The Importance of Receiving God”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - “The Last Word”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - “The Great Recovery”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - “The Great Value”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - “The Gateway to Freedom”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - “Be Still and Know”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Personal Notes & Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - “Above All Battle Lines”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Programs
  - The Fellowship of Prayer—Lenten Seasons, 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Sanctuary, Daily Devotional Readings, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Come Before Winter, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins from Various Parishes, 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Church Bulletins 1948-1956, List of Sermons Preached with Location & Date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin from Peabody College, July 22, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Peabody & Divinity Programs, 1955-1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Service Tribute Program, November 28, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Assortment of Religious Programs, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Original Artwork for Communion Table, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Assortment of Religious Programs, 1939-1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Writings
  - “Prayers Offered at the Baccalaureate Service,” Vanderbilt, Address, June 4, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Brainstorming Notes, Notes, August 2, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - “The Bible as the Basis of Protestantism”, Articles, September 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - “Introduction for the First Annual Exchange Lectureship”, Address, December 5-7, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - “I Believe in Man”, Articles, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - “Washington Story”, Address, October 6, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - “Marion Institute”, Address, May 17, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - “The First American Survey”, Essay, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - “You Tell on Yourself” & “When I Have Time”, Poems, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - “The Responsibility of Religion to the Individual”, Address, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Writing Excepts, Notes—Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous Documents/Artifacts
  - John Keith Benton’s USA Passport, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Magazine Article by Harold W. Dodd, “Christianity & Democracy,”, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Incoming letter from Everett R. Clinchy, December 18, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - John Keith Benton Assorted Photographs (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Various Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1954 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Incoming letter from Gerald F. Winfield, November 27, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Incoming letter from Otto A. Piper, September 15, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Incoming letter from Toronto, Ontario, December 21, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Incoming letter from Gastonia, N.C., December 23, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Undated letter from Alumni Association, Partial Newspaper clipping—New Yorker (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Incoming greeting card, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Personal Notes, April 23, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper & Magazine Clippings, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Article by William H. Whyte Jr., “The Wife Problem,”, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Letters about Benton’s Appointment to Vanderbilt, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Dedication of Benton Chapel (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Master Copy of Edwin Mims (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Publications by other people (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript of Dr. William B. Silverman on Spotlight Station WMAK, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Mary Gatewood Banks, “Lake Junaluska,”, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Image—Benton as a young man (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Image—Benton at Vanderbilt, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Cassette Tape—Bishop Costen Harrell talks with Roy Clark re: West End Sanctuary, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Freedom Foundation Award (Box 5, Folder 1)
- World War I Leather Aviator Helmet (Box 6, Folder 1)